Inventory of the Claude M. Owens papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Claude M. Owens papers
1940-1946
1945-1946
79084
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Legal briefs and decisions, transcripts of testimony, notes, and photographs relating to the trial of Japanese military personnel for atrocities in the Philippines during World War II.
Owens, Claude M.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Claude M. Owens earned his B.A. and law degree from Stanford University; in 1941 he was admitted to the State Bar of California. After the outbreak of World War II, he joined the United States Army, serving as a second lieutenant. He then was assigned to the prosecution division of the War Crimes Branch of the Legal Section of the Supreme Command for the Allied Powers, Manila from 1945 to 1946. After serving in the military, Owens became a Superior Court Judge.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Claude M. Owens consist of legal materials, notes, and photographs relating to the trial of Japanese military personnel, chiefly Tomoyuki Yamashita, for atrocities committed in the Philippines during World War II. Included are legal briefs prepared for prosecuting the cases and transcripts of testimony, captured diaries, sworn affidavits, and photographs prepared as evidence for use in the trial of USA vs. Yamashita.
Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers.; United States. Army; War crime trials--Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945--Atrocities.; World War, 1939-1945--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.
- Legal Briefs, 1945 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Typewritten briefs. Notations of an item number on each brief correspond to alpha and alpha-numeric index entries, found in the index in folder one. Topics covered include military orders, articles of war, criminal liability for negligence, command responsibilities, legal articles, acts pertaining to the Philippines, list of war offenses, and other documents compiled in pre-trial research.
  - Index, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Index of all of Owens' briefs, with notations on the back.
  - Legal briefs, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
    Typewritten briefs and notes on the matter of legal proceedings, prosecuting cases, and other matters in preparation for trial.
- Photographs, 1942, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  Images of non-commissioned officers in the War Crimes Branch (May 1946); second lieutenant Claude M. Owens (April 1946) and, a photo marked “Exhibit 892” (circa 1945). A large picture of the surrender meeting between General Wainwright and General Homma is also included (May 1942).
- Legal Materials, 1942-1946 (Box 2)
  Bound documents about the Philippine atrocities committed by the Imperial Japanese Army during World War II, specifically during the 1944-1945 Philippine and Pacific campaigns. The United States Army War Crimes Branch, Prosecution Division assembled these exhibits of evidence that were later compiled for use in the trial of USA vs Yamashita.
  - Exhibit number 382 to exhibit number FF, 1942 May - 1945 November (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Bound volume containing legal materials of various types that are primarily stamped or classified as exhibits of evidence in the case of USA vs Yamashita. Includes copies of personal diaries of U.S. and Japanese Imperial Army personnel; text from a United States Army report entitled “Japanese Defenses of Cities as Exemplified by the Battle for Manila” from the Headquarters of the 6th [U.S.] Army, which includes illustrations of pillboxes and other enemy construction; photographs of atrocities; a hierarchical chart of the Japanese Imperial Army; a large fold out map written in Japanese and keyed to translation by ATIS (Allied Translator and Interpreter Sections of the Southwest Pacific Area); copies of newspaper clippings of The Tribune (Manila, Philippines) from November 4, 1944 to January 31, 1945; texts of broadcasts that were intercepted, as well as testimony from informants; a notice to surrender dated May 19, 1942; and statements sworn in November 1945 from retired Japanese military generals on the character of General Tomoyuki Yamashita.
  - Exhibit number A-2 to exhibit number 381, 1945 February - 1946 August (Box-folder 2: 2)
    Bound volume containing various types of documentary evidence, primarily stamped or classified as exhibits of evidence in the case of USA vs Yamashita.
  - Exhibit number 110 to exhibit number 244, 1945 July-August (Box-folder 2: 3)
    Bound volume begininning with prosecution exhibit number 110 (the sworn testimony of Carmencita Veloso Ballesteros) and concluding with prosecution exhibit number 244 (a copy of a picture of five men pointing to a site, undated).
  - "Report of Investigation of Atrocities Committed by Japanese Imperial Forces in Intramuros (Walled City) Manila, P.I. During February 1945,", 1945 February-April (Box-folder 2: 4)
    One bound volume investigated and compiled by Colonel James T. Walsh of the Adjutant General’s Department Headquarters, XIV Corps. Compilation of exhibits of evidence composed of testimony of civilians, written statements from the priests and nuns of St. Augustine (a church), affidavits from U.S. soldiers, and pictures surrounding the places where the Japanese Imperial Army was accused of committing massacres: St. Augustine, Fort Santiago (a seized military fort), Plaza McKinley, and the Santa Rosa Ruins. Also included is documentation of the treatment of women and the Spanish who were still living in Manila at the time.
  - In re Yamashita, 327 U.S. 1, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    United States Supreme Court materials in regards to General Tomoyuki Yamashita: petitions introduced in February 1946 with court decisions, including dissenting opinions, and a memorandum dated March 1946.
- Personal Files, 1940-1946 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  Correspondence, legal documents, and a clipping from a magazine.